Guide to the Department of Computer Science records, 1961-1978
Duke University. University Archives
Department of Computer Science records 1961-1978
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Department of Computer Science.
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1500 Items
The Department of Computer Science originally formed as the Computer Science Program in 1971. It became a department in 1973. The files in this collection concern the origin and formation of the Department and include much information about the Duke University Computation Center (DUCC) and the Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC). Materials range in date from 1961-1978.
RL.01474
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
RESTRICTED: For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the director of the office of use and the University Archivist is required for use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours notice required for retrieval.
Provenance
The Department of Computer Science records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974, 1978.
Historical Note
The Computer Science Program was initiated in January 1971. It was conceived to provide courses on the theory of computer design, capabilities and use. Although students could not major in computer science at the undergraduate level, graduate courses were taught, especially in conjunction with the Engineering and Mathematics programs. By the 1973-1974 academic year, the Computer Science Program had become the Department of Computer Science, which allowed students to major in computer science and obtain a B. S.
Department of Computer Science Chairs
1971-1973 Thomas Muir Gallie, Jr., Director of the CSP
1973-1974 Merrill Lee Patrick
1974-1979 Donald W. Loveland
1979-1983 Merrill Lee Patrick
1983-1985 Thomas Muir Gallie, Jr.
1985-1992 Donald J. Rose
1992-1994 Donald W. Loveland
1994-2002 Jeffrey Vitter
2002-2005 Alan Biermann
2005- Pankaj Agarwal
Collection Overview
Contains materials regarding the origin and formation of the Department of Computer Science and includes reports, budgetary information, faculty biosketches, memos, minutes and miscellaneous items. Dates range from 1961-1978.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Computation Center; Duke University. Department of Computer Science; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Faculty; Triangle Universities Computation Center
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Thomas M. Gallie Papers, 1955-1972
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Terry Sanford Records and Papers, 1945-1998
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Undergraduate Programs1972-1978 (Box 1)
  - Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC)
  - Council Meeting Agendas1966
  - Long Range Computer Planning Committee Minutes1966-1967
  - LRP Committee - Technical Alternatives Subcommittee
  - T.U.C.C. Board of Directors, Minutes1966-1967
  - Hoyler and Rate-Setting1964-1966
  - Chaddock et al - NSF Proposal 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - NSF Proposals and Department Budgets 1969
  - T.U.C.C. - Fiscal Summaries 1961-1966
  - Patrick - NSF Proposal 1967-1970
  - Volpp Subcommittee Hearings 1968
  - Presentation to Provost Regarding T.U.C.C. 1968
  - Letters from T.U.C.C. 1966-1967
  - Letters from UNC 1966
  - Letters from NC State 1966-1967
  - Institutional Data Processing - Correspondence, Budgets, Reports 1966-1968
  - Department Progress Reports 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Department Program Information 1967-1977
  - School of Business Administration - MBA Degree 1968
  - Department of Business Administration - Proposed Courses 1969
  - Computer Science Program Information and Budget 1969-1970
  - Biographical Sketches of Computer Science Faculty
  - Computers Committees 1964-1966
  - Digital Computing Laboratory - Financial Summary Sheets 1966-1967
  - Computer Advisory Committee Memos 1967-1969
  - Review of Requirements and Resources for Computing at Duke 1969
  - Computer Planning Committee Memos 1968-1969